[Music]
okay so welcome to episode two of our
inventory system tutorial series uh in
the last episode we left it where we've
got our test item here we have a player
we can move the player over the item
we can move the player over the item and
the item data gets added to our
inventory and we've got a stack size of
one
but i hard coded it um to just directly
add itself to inventory slot zero and
this isn't the correct implementation
this was just so we could see it working
so in this video we're going to be
working on um checking whether we
can the inventory already contains the
item if it does add itself to the stack
of the item it doesn't it'll search for
a free slot in the inventory and add
itself there and if it can't do that
then obviously the backpack's full
so it will return false and nothing will
happen the item will stay on the ground
and it won't destroy itself because this
only happens
if
we return true in our add to inventory
script so in our item pickup we're
saying if
the add to inventory was successful then
destroy the object from the world
if it wasn't just do nothing so let's go
back over to our inventory system.cs
file so the two functions that we've
kind of i've mentioned so far we need to
check whether our inventory contained an
item and if it does we need to add it to
that stack and if not we need to see
whether there's a free slot so the first
thing we want we're going to do is we're
going to make a public
void
sorry we're going to make a public bull
called contains item
and this is going to take in
the inven
and this is going to take in some
inventory item data which is the uh item
to add and it's going to pass back out
an inventory slot if if one exists it's
going to pass back out the slot that the
item is contained within if
we do actually contain the item
so i'm just gonna
at the moment just to get rid of the red
squiggly line i'm just gonna set
inventory slot to null and return
false
and this is what we'll do at the end of
the
function anyway and the so the next
method we need to make is a public bull
has
free slot
and this is just going to pass back out
the very first free slot that it comes
across so uh out inventory slot free
slot
and again if it can't find a free slot
then we'll just um
we'll null out the inventory slot and
we'll return false and we'll implement
these properly in just a second let's go
back to our add to inventory script
we're going to say here
if
contains item and we're going to pass in
the
the item to add
i'm going to get back out
the inventory
slot that the item is contained in if if
it does contain the item
so if it contains the item
we're going to add to the stack of that
slot so add to stack
uh amount
well amount to add i've called it so
amount to add
and then we're going to say hey the
inventory slot has been changed so on
inventory slot changed
and we're going to say if that's
if that's been subscribed to if there's
listeners of that event if
if it's not null then
invoke it and pass through the inventory
slot that has changed
and then in our ui we can find the
corresponding actual like square slot of
the ui and we can update just that slot
and then we just want to return true now
if it doesn't contain
the item
we're going to want to check whether
it's got a free slot so else if
has free slot
and it's going to pass back out an
inventory
slot
which will be our free slot
so i'm just going to put a note here so
check whether
item exists
in inventory
gets the first
available
slot
so here we can say free slot
is equal to new slot inventory slot and
then we can pass in
the
item to add and the amount to add as
well
and then we could just say on inventory
slot changed
dot invoke
pass in our
free
slot
and actually so instead of making a new
slot here which we can just manipulate
the free slot itself directly so let's
go over to our inventory slot
and let's actually make a public void
update inventory slot and this can take
in an inventory
item data called
data and an amount
here we can just say item data is equal
to data
and stack size
is equal to amount so that way
we don't have to
destroy and make a new inventory slot we
can just
call free slot dot update inventory slot
and we can pass in the item to add
and the amount to add as well
then again we can check whether our
inventory slot changed event has
anything subscribed to it and if it does
we can invoke that event
and we can just return true because
again we were successful adding it to
our inventory and then if
we it doesn't contain the item and it
doesn't have a free slot then we just
return
false and actually after we so if we go
back to our contains item script we
don't want to just get the um slot
that um
has the item we want to get a list of
slots
so we just want to type in uh list and
then we're going to get back out and
inventory slot list
i'm going to copy this i'm just going to
put that here as well
because in this contains item method i'm
actually going to use a link function so
we're going to say that in slot is equal
to
inventory
slots
where
and we'll open up some brackets and
we'll say
i so for item
i dot data
is equal to our item to add
and then we can send that to a list
so if you haven't used um
the system.link namespace before
there's a lot of helpful stuff you can
do in inventory slots with system.link
so for example we could get inventory
slots first
and we could save the first
slot
so i could be anything so we could we
could say slot so we could say first
slot
where the slot dot item data
dot
max stack size is greater than 5
as an example so
there's a lot of stuff you can do with
system.link i highly recommend looking
more into it if you haven't come across
it before so just to make this more
human readable so
we've got inventory slots
dot where so this is going to check all
of our inventory slots
and it's going to create a list
of inventory slots and fill it
where the item
or i slot this could be anything so so
where our inventory slots item data is
equal to the item that we want to add
then just put that in a list so and this
is going to be our outlist here
and then when we're checking whether it
contains the item
we can say um return
and then we can say that does the
inventory slot dot count or is it is the
count greater than one
if the inventory slot dot count is
greater than one
then we can return true because it
obviously contains the item
and if it's less than one we can return
false because it doesn't contain the
item the item count size would be zero
so now we're getting a list back out not
an individual slot so now we need to
check those slots to see whether there
is room left in the stack
which is that method that we made
earlier on our inventory slot so like we
can now say
for each
variable slot
in
this in slot list
we're going to check does that slot have
room left in its slot
i'm going to check does that slot have
room left in stack so we say room left
in stack
and you can see we've got one of two
here these are the two overloaded
methods that we've made
we don't need to know how many are
remaining
we just need to know if we add this
amount to the stack will it fit
this amount to add here so
say amount to add
if there is room left in the stack
then
we're gonna get this
i'm gonna pop it in here but this is
gonna be called slot so it's gonna be
the slot that we're looking at in our
inventory slot list which we've got from
our contains item
so our item pickup is going to get hit
by our player and we're going to try and
add itself to the inventory in our add
to inventory script we're going to pass
through the data that we want to add to
our inventory and the amount of that
data the amount of the item that we want
to add
we're going to check with our whether
the inventory system contains this item
and if it does contain it then we're
going to get a list of all of the slots
that have the item in it
and then we're going to check that list
and we're going to check for a slot that
actually has room left in the in the
stack
if the stack's full or there's not
enough room to add so if say the maximum
stack size was five we had four
in the stack already and we were trying
to add two there wouldn't be enough room
for the two to go into the stack so we'd
check the next slot and the next to the
next and we need to get rid of the else
if here because i found that it didn't
work
as intended
when it was an elsiv
so we're going to see whether we'll
contain the item if it doesn't it'll
move on anyway and it'll check do we
have a free slot if it does contain the
item it's gonna look for the item and
see whether one of the slots
can take the amount if it can it'll
return true and call our inventory slot
changed dot invoke if it can't
then that's fine it'll move on and it'll
check for a free slot
so this should be uh all working let's
go back to the editor and
check it works and if it doesn't work
let's debug it so i'm just gonna come
back to play here
um i've got a test item i'm just gonna
make multiples of this test item now
we've got three four five six i believe
we had test item so a max stack size of
five so if we click on our play here and
we keep a track on of the inventory
system over here
and we hit play
so we're going to go over this first
item
and nothing happens
why would it work first time
let's see what the problem is here
i feel like it might be
this
issue we're having here i feel like it
might be this here this condition um
so let's just debug dot log
in slot dot count
i feel like it might be because if there
isn't anything in it the count would be
zero uh
then that list isn't gonna be
initialized
okay so we're getting
count as zero back out
what we could do instead let's
check whether this is null so
is our inventory slot
list null
if it is null then it'll be false we're
going to return false because we haven't
found anything
and if
it isn't false
and if it has found something um some
data in our inventory that equals this
item then it will return true because
this won't be null
so let's just leave that debug.log in
for now let's just see if this works
and then we'll hit play
and we'll drag our player over
oh you know what our mistake is we
haven't set up the free slot method
that's why well we're always returning
false so we can't find a free slot to
add it to
was my mistake so let's just finish this
method before we get ahead of ourselves
so here we're going to say free slot
equals
uh inventory slot
dot
slots
dot first or default which is another
system link um
method
and we're just going to say the first
inventory slot i
where the data in that slot is null so
if it's null
that inventory slot is obviously empty
and we're going to get the first slot
that
meets this criteria here and then just
like our contains item we can do
we can just return free slot
it's free slot null
so has it found a
empty slot
if it has found an empty slot
free slot would not be null so it would
be true if it hasn't found one then free
slot would be null
so it would be false and we wouldn't
have found a free slot so
let's go back over to
unity and try this now go we can add our
items as we drag our player we can see
the stack size four stack size five
so our maximum stack size is five as we
go over this next item we should go to
the next free slot which is this one
here
and there you go so stack size one this
is our new slot
if we made a another copy of this item
here
but instead we called this test
item
two
and let's just make this um let's make
another
material and we'll just call this uh
green
set it to a green color assign that here
i'm just going to swap these places
round
so our test item two here this green one
let's set that to test item two
i'm just gonna make another copy of it
here
and in our test item two we set the data
the max stack size to one
so as our player goes over we're gonna
pick up five then we're gonna pick up
one of our test item two
and then we're gonna check our inventory
for this see that we're at the maximum
stack so we'll get the next free slot
which won't be slot two because this is
going to be in it so we'll get the next
one after that so let's hit play and we
can see that all working
so let's drag our player forward so
we've got our five test item ones
test item two goes into the first free
slot that it found
test item one again but our stack size
is full so it's going to go into the
next free slot that was available it
won't go over this one or overwrite that
one and then as we go over this so the
stack size was one that's the maximum
for test item two so we've gone into the
next free slot so if i copy
these and we make another row
if i get a player and fill up our
inventory
well that filled up the inventory
no
let's um let's just set the stack size
of
test item one to one also
as we pick up these items
so our inventory is full now when we go
over these items our inventory will be
full we won't successfully add it to our
inventory so they won't delete
so you see that as we go through them
they're not coming up off the ground
because they can't successfully add
themselves to our inventory if we
deleted um an item and
made it back to its null state we could
add another item to our inventory and
it'd go into that free slot okay so
that's part two done of our inventory
system it was a bit shorter than part
one
um but we had kind of you know we'd set
up a quite a good framework in the first
video to just build upon in this second
one you can see that the functionality
is kind of now working as you would
expect so
going forward we are going to build on
the system a little bit in the back end
but we're going to start putting the ui
elements together and showing how we can
update the ui based on what is actually
in our inventory again i hope this is
all making sense so far if it's not or
you'd like anything kind of clarified
feel free to join the discord server
which is linked in the description or
leave a comment below if you're watching
these live as they come out the whole
series of this is over up on patreon
which is patreon.com forward slash
danpos you'll get the access to the full
series and all of the project files as
well to the scripts that we're building
i'm organizing the scripts by lesson in
packages so you'll be able to get the
package for the lesson that you're
following patreon is linked in the
description below as well that's
everything for this video thanks for
watching and i'll see you in the next
one bye
you